SITHEMBILE NCUBE

BSc Computer Science and Mathematics

Email: me.sithe.ncube@gmail.com Mobile: +27604865959 LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/sithencube

CAREER GOALS

Having begun my studies in a relatively new field of engineering within Africa complements the enthusiasm I have for innovation through collaboration and exploring new frontiers. I have a keen interest in using the knowledge acquired from my studies to explore the evolution of human-machine interaction in Africa and the future of gaming technology — particularly in its cultural and educational applications. After studying 2 years of a degree in Mechatronic Engineering, I am currently in my final year of a BSc in Computer Science and Mathematics.

EDUCATION

2016 - 2018: BSc Computer Science and Mathematics, Nelson Mandela University
2014 - 2015: BEng Mechatronic Engineering, Nelson Mandela Metropolitan University

EXPERIENCE

November 2016 – Present Assistant Program Manager, A MAZE GmbH

Tasked with assisting in the curation of digital art, games, electronics exhibitions, talks and performances for the annual A-MAZE playful media and art festival in Johannesburg and Berlin.

October 2014 - Present Regional Organiser, The Global Game Jam

In charge of reviewing and approving jam sites in Sub-Saharan Africa in preparation for the annual Global Game Jam. As the event approaches, sites are contacted to ensure they have the necessary communication and resources for a successful event.

July 2014 – August 2015 Google Student Ambassador, Nelson Mandela Metropolitan University

Selected to act as a liaison between Google and Nelson Mandela Metropolitan University as the school's first Google Student Ambassador.

November 2013 Organiser, Startup Weekend Lusaka

One of the 4 organisers of the first Startup Weekend Lusaka – a global grassroots movement for entrepreneurs. Managed Social Media and Graphics Design for the event.

August 2013 – Present Co-founder and Director, MakerHut

MakerHut is a user group interested in creative technologies and robotics in Zambia and making the global maker movement accessible for youth in Zambia.

July 2013 – Present Founder and Manager, Ubongo Game Lab

Founding and Managing the activities of Ubongo Game Lab, a community user group interested in Game Development and Gaming Technology in Zambia.

May 2013 – July 2013 Audio Editor, iSchool.zm

Part time responsibilities included sorting, clipping and editing of over 600 audio files for iSchool's Zedupad software. The Zedupad is an e-learning initiative that brings the Zambian Primary School Curriculum to affordable tablets.

May 2013 – December 2013 Social Media Executive, BongoHive

Managing the online presence of BongoHive, Lusaka's Technology and Innovation Hub, as well as writing weekly newsletters, graphics design and blog posts. In addition to assisting new startups establish social media strategies.

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

2007 Duke of Edinburgh Bronze

The Duke of Edinburgh program has 4 sections in order to be awarded the prestigious youth leadership award; Volunteering, Physical, Skills and Expedition. Did at least 3 months of activity for each of the Volunteering, Physical and Skills sections, and planned, trained for and underwent a 2 day (1 night) expedition for Bronze.

October 2014 3rd Place - Raspberry Pi Extravaganza, Dimension Data

Focused on the hardware interactions for a Raspberry Pi prototype of an internet controlled sprinkler game called Game of Groves under the team Game of Life. Won 3rd place and a cash prize of R5000.

December 2014 Top 50 USSA Women's Chess Championship, South Africa

Represented Nelson Mandela Metropolitan University at the USSA Women's Chess Championship 2014 and ranked 30th.

April 2015 1st Place – NASA Space Apps Challenge Port Elizabeth, NMMU

Tackled the "Space Glove" challenge set out by NASA for the International Space Apps Challenge. Designed and prototyped a glove that allows you to type and control your computer on one hand.

October 2015 2nd Place – Slice of Source Hackathon NMMU, Derivco

Took part in an 18 hour game development hackathon sponsored by Derivco. Came in 2nd place with a simple 2D stealth puzzle game.

January 2016 GDC Diversity Scholarship, Global Game Jam

From voluntary work done for the Global Game Jam in underrepresented regions, awarded an all-access pass to attend the annual Game Developers' Conference in San Francisco.

May 2017 Miss. Africa Seed Fund Grant, DotConnectAfrica

Awarded \$1000 seed fund grant for Games Plus Girls Initiative with Ubongo Game Lab. Part of a 1 year partnership with Miss.Africa to promote opportunities for women in STEM.

July 2017 MILEAD Fellowship, Moremi Initiative

Selected as one of 26 women in Africa recognized as promising emerging young leaders. The fellowship involves an intensive 3-week leadership institute in Ghana and each fellow is required to develop a Mi-CHANGE Project addressing a selected issue within their community.

COMMUNITY SERVICE

2015 – Present: Game Development Training, Asikana Network

Created and delivered a short curriculum for the intensive 'Games Plus Girls' Bootcamp that teaches rapid game prototyping to women in order to increase participation in the annual Global Game Jam.

2005 – 2009: Tutoring, Various schools

Literacy lessons, exam preparation and conducting science experiments for students ranging from 5 to 16 in surrounding rural schools as a devotional service.

PUBLIC SPEAKING

March 2016 Game Developers Conference 2016 - San Francisco, California

As part of a diverse panel I was given the opportunity to speak on the prospects of game development in Zambia and Sub-Saharan Africa. The panel talk is publically available online: http://www.gdcvault.com/play/1023582/

September 2016 AMAZE – Johannesburg, South Africa

Spoke in front of an international audience at the AMAZE Playful Media and Arts festival on building game development communities in third world countries.

HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

Electronics: Enjoys working with microcontrollers and hobby electronics including Raspberry Pi and Arduino

Game Development: Creates small games for fun and participates in various game jams.

Gamification: Interested in the social and educational applications of gaming technology